Nishanth Solomon

+14809302842 • nsolomo2@asu.edu • nishanthsolomon.github.jo • https://www.linkedin.com/in/nishanthsolomon/

SUMMARY

Graduate student and versatile programmer with 2+ years of research in Natural Language Processing, Deep Learning, and work experience in end-to-end Development and Deployment of Software as a Service(SaaS) and seeking a full-time position as a software developer starting in May 2021.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Robotics and Autonomous Systems August 2019 - May 2021

Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ 3.96/4

Bachelor of Engineering in Mechanical

July 2013 - May 2017 Anna University, Chennai, India 8.11/10.0

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, Java, JavaScript, Matlab, C/C++, Bash

Databases, and OS: PostgreSQL, MySQL, Windows, Linux/Ubuntu

Libraries: AllenNLP, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, NLTK, spaCy, Scikit-Learn, Tools, and Frameworks: Git (GitHub, GitLab), Cherrypy, Flask, Elasticsearch

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Zoho Corporation, Chennai, India Software Developer

May 2017 - July 2019

Natural Language Processing: Research and implementation of Neural Networks

- Developed NLP models for Multi-class Classification, Named Entity Recognition, Language Detection.
- Analyzed Elasticsearch queries and improved the search quality by introducing the shingle analyzer.
- Organized client meetings and defined functional and technical requirements.

DevOps: Responsible for deploying and scaling REST APIs and maintaining servers in 4+ data centers.

- Delivered NLP models as micro-services and maintained a network of 50+ Linux servers with 99.9% up-time.
- Configured PostgreSQL, designed table models, formulated access APIs and implemented full-text search.
- Managed GitLab repositories and permissions and created a chatbot with webhooks to keep the team updated.

PROJECTS

Al12 Reasoning Challenge Arizona State University

February 2020 - April 2020

- Initiated Information Retrieval and Prediction modules with Elasticsearch and language models.
- Implemented code to support GPU inferencing and reduced the prediction time by 1/10th.
- Reviewed the failed cases and implemented new methods to increase the accuracy by 15%.
- Trained the XLNet Model on the RACE dataset using Google Colab and experimented with new models.

Question Answering System Zoho Corporation

January 2019 - May 2019

- Deployed a system to automatically answer FAQs from a set of predefined FAQs stored in PostgreSQL.
- Created REST APIs, automated API testing using postman runner, and interfaced with clients.
- Designed tables, configured databases, and provided support with maintenance and documentation.
- Coordinated with support engineers, to replace the monotonous work of answering fundamental guestions.

Industry Classification Zoho Corporation

September 2018 - December 2018

- Constructed a model using AllenNLP to classify free-text documents into predefined categories.
- Assessed the data, improved the cleaning pipeline, and experimented with classification techniques.
- Re-engineered the problem to improve performance and achieved about 91% accuracy to predict 45 classes.
- Increased the speed of cleaning the data by optimizing and implementing parallel processing in production.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ Research Aide

August 2020 - Present

- Extracted moderation rules from Reddit emails using pandas and TF-IDF vectors after preprocessing.
- Executed data cleaning methods using spaCy, textacy to extract information from the Reddit dataset.
- Converted classification of content moderator emails to the rule violated into a BERT model.
- Compared moderation emails and compiled methods to build trust in people to accept AI moderated emails.
- Retrofitted a bag-of-words model to find Political Polarization using Reddit User data.
- Experimented with tuning a neural network to classify users based on their interaction with the subreddits.